<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godly sermon preached in Latin at great S. Maries in Cambridge, in Marche 1580. by Robert Some: and translated by himselfe into English</title>
            <author>Some, Robert, 1542-1609.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1580</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12590</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22907</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100971</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836798</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836798</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1086</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12590)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1086)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1188:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godly sermon preached in Latin at great S. Maries in Cambridge, in Marche 1580. by Robert Some: and translated by himselfe into English</title>
                  <author>Some, Robert, 1542-1609.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Henrie Middleton, for George Bishop,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1580.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1086:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ A Godly Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon preached in Latin <hi>at great S. Maries in</hi> Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, in Marche 1580. by <hi>Robert Some:</hi> and tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by himſelfe <hi>into</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MARKE 1.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Repent and beleeue the Goſpel.</p>
            </q>
            <p>¶ Imprinted by Henrie Middleton, for <hi>George Biſhop.</hi> 1580.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1086:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1086:2"/>
            <head>To the Right worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Maſter William Killigrew <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier, one of her Maiesties priuie Chamber</hi> and Myſtreſſe Margerie Killigrew his wife, <hi>R. Some</hi> wiſheth increaſe of Gods gifts to their euerlaſting comfort.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath pleaſed your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips to vſe me very frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I am verie mindefull of it, and for ſome proofe of my thankfulneſſe, I offer to you that ſhorte Sermon in Engliſh, which I preſented in Latine to the Right honourable the Earle of Leiceſter, my ſingular good Lorde and Maſter. It is, I confeſſe verie plaine, and my deſire was ſo to haue it: but it will, I am ſure, miniſter comfort by the grace of God to ſuche as haue a feeling of their ſinnes. And this either is, or ſhould be one prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall drifte of our ſermons, eſpecially in
<pb facs="tcp:1086:3"/> theſe daies, wherein as many as are to be awaked out of the ſleepe of ſinne by Gods fearefull threatenings ſo other are to be rayſed vp, and muſt haue life put into them by Gods ſweete promiſes. I could eaſily, and would like well to goe on in this argument, if it were not both the butte and white that my Sermon principally doeth leuell at. Vnto the which becauſe I referre your ſelfe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Killigrew, and your good bedfel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, I take my leaue and commend you both to Almightie Gods tuition. Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge the 20 of April. <hi>1580.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your worſhips to command in Chriſt,</hi> Robert Some.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1086:3"/>
            <head>A Godlie Sermon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in Latine at great Saint Maries <hi>in Cambridge, in March. 1580. by</hi> Robert Some: and tranſlated by himſelfe into Engliſh.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>That all may be done to Gods glorie and our edifying, let vs pray to his Maieſtie, that his holie worde, which is a most pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious treaſure be not as a <hi>ſhut booke,</hi> and as a <hi>ſealed</hi> letter vnto vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="epigraph">
               <head>THE TEXT.</head>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Hoſeas Chap. 14. ver. 3.4.</bibl>
                  <p>Take vnto you wordes, and turne to the Lord and ſay to him, take away al in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquitie, and receiue (vs) graciouſly, ſo wil we render the calues of our lippes. Aſſhur ſhall not ſaue vs, neither will we ride vpon horſes, neither will we ſay any more to the worke of our hands, ye are our Gods, for in thee the fatherleſſe findeth mercie.</p>
               </q>
               <pb facs="tcp:1086:4"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe two verſes may be reduced vnto two partes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the firſt the Prophete exhorteth the Iſraelites vnto repentance, and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth them what wordes to vſe in their prayer to the Maieſtie of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>Take vnto you wordes, and turne to the Lord, and ſay to him, take away all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquitie, and receiue (vs) gratiouſly.</p>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the ſecond part he ſetteth out the fruites of repentance in liuely colours.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>So will we render the calues of our lips. Aſſhur ſhall not ſaue vs, neither will wee ride vpon horſes, neither will we ſay any more to the worke of our handes, ye are our Gods: for in thee the fatherleſſe findeth mercie.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="sermon">
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake vnto you wordes.</hi> The eternal god beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many benefites vpon the Iſraelites, euen with both the handes: but they were as vntamed horſes. When they
<pb facs="tcp:1086:4"/> were fatted, they lifted vp their héeles againſt his Maieſtie, and would not be reclaimed by his moſt pleaſaunt voyce. The Lord perceiuing the Iſraelites to reſemble the <hi>Aethiopian,</hi> which retay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his blackneſſe, though he be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed an hundred times: and the <hi>Catt of mountaine,</hi> which is not cléere of ſpots though hir ſkinne be taken from hir: the lord, I ſay, dealt more ſharply with them, and to knotty woodde applied a wedge of Iron. Amongſt theſe light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and as it were, thunderboltes of Gods iudgementes, leaſt the faithfull which had forgotten themſelues ſhould be diſcouraged, and thinke that no hope of pardon remained, he ſpeaketh vnto them (as a naturall father to his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren) moſte louingly, by his Prophete, <hi>Take vnto you wordes,</hi> as if he ſhoulde ſay, albéeit you haue infected the earth and aire with the ſtench of your wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, albéeit you are more filthy than the dunghilles, hange not downe your heades, vnleſſe you be ſet to wallow ſtil in the mire of your ſinnes. You ſhal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſſe Gods anger, not if you bring into
<pb facs="tcp:1086:5"/> his preſence great ſtore of golde and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, heapes of frankinſence, droues of Oxen, and flockes of Shéepe, but if you preſent vnto him <hi>wordes</hi> which may eaſily be come by. The Prophet <hi>Hoſeas</hi> ſpeaketh not of <hi>fained wordes,</hi> which cunning and holow hypocrites are wel acquainted with.<note place="margin">Gen. 3.4. Eſay. 58.3. Matt. 22.16. Iere. 41.6.</note> Such were the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the ſerpent vnto Eue: of the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites which faſted in Eſaies time: of the Herodians and Phariſées diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that they might ſnare Chriſt in his ſpéech: of vngracious Iſmael to the god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly men of Sichem and Samaria, when he ſhed Crocodyles teares before he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried them to the ſlaughter: and of many now a dayes, whoſe wordes are bredde and borne in their lippes. Diſſembling words are the greateſt plague that can be, they ſmell of an euil conſcience, they are ſure arguments of hypocriſie, and doe them which vſe them the greateſt harme: for they are like to a broken ſhielde, which cannot abide y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt prick of a weapon. The prophet Hoſeas did not giue the Iſraelites in charge to put of the groſſe contempt of God, &amp; to cloth
<pb facs="tcp:1086:5"/> themſelues with hipocriſy: that had ben the next way to haue marred all, and of euill men to make them diuels: he ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commaunded them to teſtifie god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily in holy &amp; ſounde wordes, that which they had conceiued moſt holily in their mindes. There muſt not be a diuorce betwene the heart and the lippes: they muſt reſemble <hi>Hippocrates twinnes,</hi> which do laugh together, and wéepe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. The minde muſt beget godly wordes, &amp; the lippes bring them forth. This is a golden broode, &amp; highly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth almighty God. Such was the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the <hi>Primatiue Church</hi> for Peter,<note place="margin">Actes. 12.5. Iames. 5.17. Mat. 27.46. 2. Cor. 12.8.</note> when <hi>Herode Agrippa</hi> had impriſoned him: of Helias, which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle Iames remembreth: of Chriſt hanging on the croſſe: and of the Apoſtle Paule when the Angell of Satan did buffet him. Such a praier would the Prophet Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeas haue the Iſraelites to vſe in this place, that Gods anger by this beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full conſent of the heart and lips, might be appeaſed. Such a praier muſt ours be, vnleſſe we will be like to Barge or Whirimen, which row one way, &amp; loke
<pb facs="tcp:1086:6"/> another. Demoſthenes and Cicero were famous Orators, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one in Athens the other in Rome. I confeſſe they were able to worke great maſteries by their eloquence. Their orations were great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accompted of in Rome and Athens, and are in good credite with vs. But if they be compared with the broken and vnperfect ſpéeches of a truly repentant ſinner, Demoſthenes wordes muſt ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d behind the dore, and Ciceroes are with out life, and are as farre excéeded, as the Pibble ſtone of the coſtly Diamonde. <hi>The ſacrifices of God are a contrite ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.17.</note> 
                  <hi>a contrite and a broken heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And turne to the Lord.</hi> To deſerue well of other, is not the leaſt of the due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of this life. To helpe euery man as he nedeth help, is a very ſinguler thing. He that relieueth the poore, doeth well: he that deliuereth them out of priſon which are in fetters there, doth better: but he that leadeth them which are, as it were, paſt grace, out of the ſhadow of death into the light of life, deſerueth beſt of all. <hi>Aegypt</hi> was barren when <hi>Nilus</hi> did not ouerflow it: <hi>Mount Sion</hi> was
<pb facs="tcp:1086:6"/> barren when it was not watered with dew from Heauen: but without godly admonition, which is like to a precious and ſwéete ſmelling ointment, men do rot in wickednes, and do cal a thouſand euils to themſelues. <hi>Hoſeas</hi> leaſt the Iſraelites which had giuen Gods glory a gréeuous blow, ſhould euer be at war with the eternal God, and at the length be ſtricken through with Gods ſworde as they deſerued, calleth them to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>Turne to the Lord,</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, you are the ſonnes of Abraham: albéeit you haue forgotten your ſelues, and haue wraſtled with the Lorde, caſt from you the weapons of monſtrous wickednes, neither continue battaile with him, which with an iron rodd can breake wilde beaſtes in péeces, and doth with ſtretched out armes imbrace re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant ſinners. The Prophet Eſay when he had dealte ſharpely with the Iewes for running in their diſtreſſe to <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and ſo caſting themſelues head long to hell: leaſt they ſhould ſtill be pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners to Sathan, who is a wily Fox, and did mightely beſtirre himſelfe to
<pb facs="tcp:1086:7"/> bar them of all hope of pardon, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Eſay, I ſay, calleth them to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.<note place="margin">Eſay. 31.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Turne againe O ye children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, in as much as ye are ſunken deepe in rebellion.</hi> Ieremie when he had liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; in Orient colours ſet out the mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Iſraelites touching Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and had grieuouſly complayned that they had broken their faith with God, like vnto filthie ſtrompets: leaſt they ſhould euer runne awrie, if they did ſée the gates of Gods mercie ſhut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, he cried alowde in Gods name, that pardon was readie for them: <hi>Thou diſobedient Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iere. 3.12.14.</note> 
                  <hi>returne, ſaith the Lord:</hi> and a litle after: <hi>O ye diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient children, turne againe ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord for I am your husband.</hi> The ſpirite of God hauing roundly taken vp the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of the Church of Epheſus, becauſe <hi>He had left his firſt loue,</hi> before he will put any puniſhment in execution, he commandeth him to repent:<note place="margin">Reuel. 2.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Remember from whence thou art fallen and repent, and do the firſt works: or elſe I wil come againſt thee ſhortly, and wil remoue thy candleſtick out of his place, except thou
<pb facs="tcp:1086:7"/> amend.</hi> We muſt treade in the ſteppes of Eſay, Ieremie, Hoſeas: when we will caſte downe the rotten walles of ſinne, we muſt in any wiſe remember to call greeuous ſinners vnto repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. When the ſinner is amended we muſt deale louingly with him:<note place="margin">Luke. 10.34. 2. Cor. 2.10.11.</note> we muſt vſe oyle with the Samaritane, &amp; with S. Paul which gaue eſpeciall charge to them of Corinth, to receiue againe into the boſome of their Church the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate Corinthian, after his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment. They which take not this courſe, that is to ſay, they whiche deale hardly and roughly with them whiche are wounded with the feeling of ſinne, doe them as much good, as ſmoake doth the eyes, and as the Eaſt winde doeth the fruites of the earth, and are hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites though they thunder a thouſand times in the pulpits. And becauſe they know not what it is to féele the heauie hand of God, howſoeuer they haue the countenance of Cato, they doe in déede reſemble Iſmael and Nero. I ſpeak not this, that ſinne which is too too riſe ſhold more increaſe, but becauſe I would
<pb facs="tcp:1086:8"/> haue the miniſters trie euerie way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they condemne other to hell, and barre againſt them the doore of Gods mercie with Aceſius,<note place="margin">Socrat. lib. 1. Cap. 10.</note> which was one of wicked Nouatus his ſchollers. The eternall God is verie gratious, if we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire his fauour: he giueth to the repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant <hi>milke,</hi> as it were, out of his breſts. He that found his loſt ſheepe, laide it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his ſhoulders, and was a glad man. The woman when ſhe had found her loſt grote, was as ioyfull as might be. The prodigall young man by riot and diſſolute behauiour beeing brought to a verie lowe ebbe, returned with greate humilitie to his father. Did the olde man entertain him as <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth did <hi>Henrie</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperor?<note place="margin">Benno Cardi.</note> if he had, he had marred the faſhion of his ſonne which was mightily gréeued: but let vs heare what the Euangeliſt Luke ſaith: <hi>When he was yet a great way of,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke. 15.20.21.22.23.24.</note> 
                  <hi>his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſawe him, and had compaſſion, and ranne and fell on his necke,</hi> He did not treade on his ſonnes necke as Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the thirde did vpon the Emperour Frederikes, <hi>And kiſſed him,</hi> not as
<pb facs="tcp:1086:8"/> Ioab did Amaſa, and Iudas Chriſte. When the father hearde this ſpéech of his ſonne, <hi>Father I haue ſinned againſt heauen and before thee, &amp; am no more worthie to be called thy ſonne,</hi> He did not reuile his ſonne, or caſt in his diſhe his former vnthriftineſſe, but, <hi>ſaide to his ſeruantes: bring forth the beſt robe</hi> not ſuch a one as Dianeira is ſaide to haue giuen to her huſbande Hercules, imbrued in the bloud of the Centaure: <hi>And put it on him, and put a ring on his hand,</hi> not ſuch a one as bloudie Gyges had, <hi>and bring,</hi> not an Italian fig, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, poiſon in a golden cup, <hi>but the fat calf &amp; &amp; kil him, and let vs eate &amp; be merry, for this my ſonne was dead, and is aliue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: and he was loſt, but he is found.</hi> If the earthly father did ſo fréely pardon a riotous and graceleſſe vnthrifte, and in ſteede of his ragges, clothe him in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſorte, we may aſſure our ſelues that God will burie our ſinnes, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh vs againe with thoſe good giftes which for our naughtineſſe he did ſtrip vs of. The great goodneſſe of God, if it he compared with the earthly Fathers,
<pb facs="tcp:1086:9"/> doeth as farre paſſe it, as the maine ſea doth a de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p of water:<note place="margin">Eſay. 65.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Yea before they call, I will anſwere, ſaith the Lorde. And ſay to him, take away all iniquitie.</hi> Hoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as dealt before with the Iſraelites, <hi>To take wordes vnto them and to turne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lorde,</hi> If a word more had not paſſed from him, the Iſraelites had bene greatly in his debt: but when he ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his heart vnto them, and teacheth them what wordes they ſhould vſe, to winne Gods fauour, they owe no leſſe then themſelues to the Prophet. As Hoſeas, ſo did Dauid, Ioel, Chriſt. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid when he had highly commended Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, for that it was a bond of holie vnitie, a barborough of the Church, and the ſeate of the kingdome: that that ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie béeing, watred with Gods bleſſing as with pleaſaunt ſtreames, might euer flouriſh like the palme trée: he teacheth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly how to pray for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> happie eſtate of the holy citie:<note place="margin">Pſal. 122.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Pray for the peace of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let them proſper that loue thee.</hi> The Prophet Ioel, leaſt the Aſſirians army ſhould (as a great ſtood) ſwallow vp the tribe of Iuda, plagued before of
<pb facs="tcp:1086:9"/> God by famine for their ſinnes, calleth them earneſtly to faſting and teares: &amp; leaſt they ſhold be dumbe in this excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t action, he giueth the prieſtes in charge to pray thus vnto the maieſtie of God. <hi>Spare thy people O Lorde,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioel. 2.16.17.</note> 
                  <hi>and giue not thy heritage into reproch, that the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then ſhould rule ouer them.</hi> Our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, leaſt his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples in praying ſhould fall into the vaine repetitions, and much babling of the heathen, deliuered to them a ſhorte, but yet an excellent forme of praier in theſe wordes, <hi>Our Father which art in Heauen &amp;c.</hi> As Dauid, Ioel, Chriſt, and Hoſeas did, ſo muſt we. If we ſhal haue to do with them which are contrite and broken in ſpirite, it is not inough to ſpeake thus vnto them, <hi>pray to the lord, pray to the lorde, pray to the lorde,</hi> but we muſt teach them with what words they may procure his fauour. So ſhall we heale a wounded conſcience, and it will eaſily appéere, that we haue appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our plaiſter aright with the ſkilfull Surgian, and our medicine aright with the learned Phiſician.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take away all iniquitie.</hi> This is an
<pb facs="tcp:1086:10"/> excellent prayer, and conſiſtes of two parts. In the firſt, the Iſraelits confeſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei dranke iniquitie as water: in the ſecond part thei deſire pardon. The firſt part is conteined in theſe wordes, <hi>all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquitie:</hi> the ſeconde, in theſe wordes, <hi>take away.</hi> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the firſt, the Iſraelits dealt very Chriſtianly when they gaue ſentence againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues &amp; ſpared not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the Lord might ſpare them. If they had pleaded <hi>not guiltie,</hi> and had impudently cried that they had not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the maieſtie of God, they had loſt their labour, &amp; had reached him an iron rod to beate them in péeces with. Nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble therfore is that ſpéech of the prophet Dauid:<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.5.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſaid, I will confeſſe againſt my ſelfe my wickednes vnto the Lord.</hi> The Iſraelites being diſperſed vnder the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Antiochus,</hi> vſed this ſpéech vnto the Lord:<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.6.</note> 
                  <hi>We haue ſinned with our fathers, we haue committed iniquitie and done wickedly.</hi> Ezra, Iob, Nehemias, and the Publicane did the like. So muſt we do, euen fréely and from the heart. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our faultes muſt be our medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine when we haue done amiſſe, as it was to the Iſraelites. We hate thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:1086:10"/> impudent fellowes, which are either dainty, or refuſe to confeſſe thoſe things which are in euery mans eyes &amp; mouth. Gods eies cannot be dazeled: vnleſſe we confeſſe our ſinnes, we deceaue not the Lord, but our ſelues: we hide our ſelues with Adam amongſt the trées, and with Figge leaues we do cloath our ſelues. The Iſraelites in this excellent petici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>take away all iniquitie,</hi> do not onely giue out that thei are guilty of one falt, but that their wickednes (like a great flood) ouerfloweth them. Ezra, when the Iſraelites after their returne from captiuitie in Babylon, had ioyned in mariage with the daughters of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites, Ammonites, Egyptians, is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to remember only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrange ſinne which the lord God hated deadly, but ſpreading out his hands to the lord he burſt into theſe words:<note place="margin">Ezra. 9.5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are increaſed ouer our heade, &amp; our treſpaſſe is growen vp vnto the heauen.</hi> Dauid when he was touched in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for the vniuſt ſlaughter of Vrias, and for betraying the Lords armie, did not only cruſh that Byle, but confeſſeth himſelfe to be further plunged in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes:
<pb facs="tcp:1086:11"/> 
                  <hi>Deliuer me from bloud,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.14.</note> 
                  <hi>O God &amp;c.</hi> They that haue offended God by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny notable ſinne, if they will ſeriouſly call the reſt of their life to a reckoning, it wil be cléere vnto them, that their ſins cannot be told on their fingers, or truſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp in a fardel: and therfore thei muſt cry with the prophet Dauid:<note place="margin">Pſal. 11.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Who can vnderſtand his faultes: cleanſe me from my ſecrete faultes.</hi> I could if I liſted, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry longer in this argument, but bicauſe I deſire to be bréefe, and yet to haue va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie, I will remember in a worde or two, that the Iſraelits after the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their ſinnes, deſired pardon. The confeſſion of our ſinnes ſauoureth of a good and godly minde: but vnleſſe deſire of pardon be ioyned with it, we ſaile in a ſhipp that hath a hole in the bottome. Cain, after that he had murdered his brother Abel, gaue out this ſpéech: <hi>My ſinne is greater then can be pardoned.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 4.13.</note> Iudas after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had betrayed his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 27.4.</note> ſaid: <hi>I haue ſinned betraying the innocent blood.</hi> But bicauſe Cain &amp; Iudas did here, as it were, ride at an anchor, they made ſhipwracke of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life. The Iſraelites, of whom
<pb facs="tcp:1086:11"/> Hoſeas ſpeaketh, were not of the ſame pariſh y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Cain &amp; Iudas were: thei deſire pardon. It profiteth not the wounded man to looke on his woundes, vnleſſe he call for a Surgian, neither the ſick man to know his diſeaſe, vnleſſe he cal for the Phiſician: I will add a third thing, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth the hatred of ſinne profite the ſicke &amp; wounded ſinner, vnleſſe he craue for mercy at the hands of God, the moſt ſkilfull both Phiſician &amp; Surgian. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid when the ſtaffe of his ſinnes had ſo galled his heart, that he felt, as it were, a gréeuous hell within him, both hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and earneſtly deſireth pardon:<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.1.2.7 9.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, O God, according to thy louing kindnes: according to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of thy compaſſions put away mine iniquities. Waſh me throughly from mine iniquitie, &amp; cleanſe me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſin. Purge me with Hiſop, &amp; I ſhalbe cleane: waſh me and I ſhalbe whiter than ſnow, hide thy face from my ſinnes, and put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all mine iniquities. Deliuer me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> blood O God &amp;c:</hi> Daniel when the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites had béen longe in captiuitie at Babylon, deſireth pardon of his &amp; their ſinnes, and that it would pleaſe the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie
<pb facs="tcp:1086:12"/> of God to perform his promiſe for their return fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Babilon: <hi>O Lord heare O Lord forgiue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Daniel. 9.19.</note> 
                  <hi>O Lord conſider &amp; do it, deferr not for thine owne ſake, O my God.</hi> The Publicane in the Goſpel, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>béeit he durſt not lift vp his eies to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, yet he ſmote his breſt, &amp; deſired for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of his ſinnes:<note place="margin">Luke. 18.13.</note> 
                  <hi>O God be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful to me a ſinner.</hi> We our ſelues gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> burden of our ſinnes, muſt hunger and thirſt for the grace of God, &amp; therefore craue pardon of our ſinnes. Almightie God is not ſuch a one as Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos or Rhadamanthus was: he is not a iudge that will not be intreated: <hi>He is therefore mercifull bicauſe he is God.</hi> The lawes of Draco the Athenia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were written with blood:<note place="margin">Ariſtot. pol. 2.</note> nothing in them is worthy of remembrance but extremitie of puniſhment. But Gods lawes are written with milke.<note place="margin">Pſal. 130.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Mercy is with God that he may be feared. Aske and it ſhal be giuen you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 7.7.</note> 
                  <hi>ſeeke and ye ſhall finde, knock,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>and it ſhalbe opened vnto you.</hi> If any plain dealing ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhold giue out to his debters y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he would for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their debt, would they ſo much as thinke of paying that creditor? if god
<pb facs="tcp:1086:12"/> hath ſet it downe in his worde, that he will pardon repentant ſinners, do we thinke that he wil not kéepe touch with them?<note place="margin">Nomb. 23.19.</note> 
                  <hi>God is not as man that he ſhould lie, neither as the ſonne of man that he ſhould repent: hath he ſaide and ſhall he not do it, &amp; hath he ſpoken and ſhal not he accompliſh it?</hi> as it is in Balaams parable to Balak, the Kinge of Moab. <hi>Though your ſinnes were as crymſin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay. 1.18.</note> 
                  <hi>they ſhalbe made white as ſnow: though they were red like ſcarlet, they ſhalbe as wooll,</hi> ſaith the lord. Much more might be fetched out of the rich ſtorehouſe of Gods booke, but I haue done with this argument, when I haue added theſe ſwéet and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable ſpéeches,<note place="margin">Mich. 7.19. Pſal. 32.1.</note> 
                  <hi>that God doeth not remember our ſinnes, that he caſtes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the botom of the ſea, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he layeth them not to our charge, but doth couer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. 52.</note> If therfore God hath couered ſinnes, he would not caſt his eye vpon them: if he would not caſt his eie vpon them, he would not throughly conſider of them: if he would not throughly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of them, he woulde not puniſhe them: he would not know them, but had rather pardon them.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1086:13"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>And receiue vs graciouſly.</hi> The va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lew of good things is better knowne by the want, then by the continuall hauing of them. Helth is ſwéeter to them which are recouered after gréeuous ſickneſſe, then to them which were neuer ſicke. Riches are more pleaſant to poore men which were ſomtimes wealthy, then to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> which neuer knewe what wante meaned. The Iſraelites when they were plagued with want &amp; beggery for their manifolde tranſgreſſions, after pardon craued for their ſinnes, do hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly &amp; earneſtly deſire at the lords hands that <hi>he would deale gratiouſly with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> that is to ſay, that he would reach his hand to them and water the withered Iſraelites with the ſtreams of his libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie.<note place="margin">Iob. 8.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Can a ruſh grow without myne, or can the graſſe grow without water?</hi> as Bildad ſaid to Iob. Vnleſſe almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God do make the riuers of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe paſſe vnto vs, we are like to a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched bladder. If God bleſſe not our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, our early riſings will not ſerue the turne: for the heauen ſhalbe as iron, and the earth as an armed ſouldiour to execute Gods iudgements, and he that
<pb facs="tcp:1086:13"/> earneth wages, ſhall put it in a broken purſe. But when God doth fauour vs, it goeth well with vs, we haue welth at will, &amp; in a ground, as it were, barren, faire corne, &amp; a beautifull Vine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vp. Moſes, leſt the Iſraelites whom he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended for their godlines, ſhould ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reuolte or wax faint in the midſt of their race, doth ſingularly harten them: <hi>God will loue thee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 7.13.</note> 
                  <hi>and bleſſe thee and multiply thee: he wil alſo bleſſe the fruit of thy wombe, and the fruit of thy land, thy corne, and thy wine, and thy oyle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Prophet Ioel, that the tribe of Iuda béeing now turned to the Lorde might put off the mourning wéede, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lords mouth great ſtore of temporall bleſſings.<note place="margin">Ioel. 2.24.</note> 
                  <hi>The barnes ſhal be full of wheate, &amp; the preſſes ſhal abound with wine &amp; oyle.</hi> Hoſeas, that the Iſraelites might aſſure themſelues of Gods fauour, deliuereth the Lordes minde verie comfortably to them, <hi>I wil breake the bowe and the ſworde,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſeas. 2.18.21.22.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; the battel out of the earth, and will make them to ſleepe ſafely: and in that day I wil heare, ſaith the Lord, I wil heare the heauens, and they ſhall heare the earth,
<pb facs="tcp:1086:14"/> &amp; the earth ſhal heare the corne, and the wine, and the oyle, and they ſhall heare Izreel.</hi> And that theſe ſwéet promiſes might take déep roote in the harts of the Iſraelites, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet Hoſeas, or rather the Lord by the prophete handleth the ſame argument in the laſt Chapter of that prophecie: <hi>I will loue them freely: I wil be as the deawe vnto Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſeas. 14.5.6.7.8.</note> 
                  <hi>he ſhal growe as the lillie, &amp; faſten his rootes as the trees of Lebanon his branches ſhall ſpread, and his beawtie ſhall be as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue tree, and his ſmel as Lebanon. They y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dwel vnder his ſhadowe, ſhal returne: they ſhall reuiue as the corne and floriſh as the vine: the ſente thereof ſhall be as the wine of Lebanon.</hi> When Almightie God hath put away our ſins as a cloud, and hath made the beautifull ſonne of his grace to ſhine vnto vs, he féedeth the hungrie, clotheth the naked, healeth our diſeaſes bleſſeth our ſtudies, &amp; doth lade vs with heaps of benefits. God is neuer wearie with doing vs good. His ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe cannot be emptied and his foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine can neuer be dried vp.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And we wil render the calues of our lips.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A good turne muſt be remembred, and
<pb facs="tcp:1086:14"/> we muſt be thankful to him that hath deſerued wel of vs. If any haue done vs good, either by preferring vs, or deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vs from daunger, we may not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the pleaſure done vnto vs, and it is in euerie mans mouth that we muſt i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate the fruitful fieldes, which bring forth more corn then they receiued. The eternal God did powre infinit bleſſings vpon the Iſraelites, as it were with a full horne: he planted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a noble vine: when they brought forth wilde grapes, the Lorde did prune and cut the vine. When they caſte them ſelues headlong to all vngodlines, he pulled them often back with the bridle of his feare: he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaue them infinite ſins and laded them with externall benefits. The Iſraelites hauing receiued large meaſure of Gods bleſſinges, giue out y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wil be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly thankfull to his Maieſtie: <hi>We will render,</hi> ſaide they, <hi>the calues of our lips,</hi> as if they ſhould ſay, in the time of the lawe they offered calues when they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed their vowes: but in ſtéede of offering calues, we will render the calues of our lips, that is to ſay, we wil praiſe &amp; commend the goodnes of God.
<pb facs="tcp:1086:15"/> The prophete Dauid, when the Lord had turned his mourning into ioy, &amp; his ſackecloth into gladnes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 30.11.12.</note> giueth out that he was therfore gratiouſly dealt with, that he might be alwayes a trompet of the praiſes of God. And in another place after that he had taſted or rather dronk déeply of gods ſingular goodnes, he bruſt out into theſe wordes.<note place="margin">Pſal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 69.30.31.</note> 
                  <hi>I wil prayſe the name of God with a ſong, and magnifie him with thankeſgiuing: this alſo ſhall pleaſe the Lord better then a yong bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke that hath hornes and hoofes.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ioel prophecied, the graſſehoppers, the canker wormes &amp; the caterpillers were the Lords armie to deſtroy all the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites increaſe. The Iſraelites were for a time ſhrewdly pinched, &amp; hungerbit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: but the Lord at the length had mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie on them. And when he had made the earth verie fruiteful, the Iſraelites are called on to be thankful to his Maieſtie <hi>You ſhal prayſe the name of the Lorde your god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath dealt maruelouſly with you.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioel. 2.26.</note> But let vs leaue the Iſraelites, &amp; a little while examine our ſelues. The e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall God hath ben verie gratious, &amp; good to the vniuerſitie of Cambridge, his
<pb facs="tcp:1086:15"/> pleaſure was &amp; is, to haue it an orcharde of moſt precious fruite, a temple of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and a chappel of godlines. Are we thankeful to God for his ſingular good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes? If we will be truely thankfull, we may not burie the Lordes treaſure in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, &amp; hide his light vnder a buſhel, &amp; like the harper Aſpendius plaie and ſing onely to our ſelues. If we will be truly thankful, if any in our Colledges be ſuſpected of Poperie, we muſt teach them Gods trueth, if they be willing to learne it: if they refuſe to be taught, we muſt expell them. If we will be truely thankfull, we muſt make much of poore mens ſonns which are toward &amp; godly, &amp; we muſt take héed, that Colledge pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fréely to the worthieſt, &amp; be not chopped or changed for monie. If we will be truely thankfull, we may not preferre bolde and idle fukes which are fitter for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cart, then for their books, &amp; neuer knew what good learning ment we may not, I ſay, ſet them ouer the painefull Bées in the vniuerſitie, and Colledge hiues, vnleſſe we will deale ſtrangely, which God forbid, with the Church and common wealth. For as the
<pb facs="tcp:1086:16"/> couer is for the ſhielde, and the ſheath, for the ſword,<note place="margin">Lib. 2. De nat. De.</note> as Chriſippus ſaid: ſo V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſitie Coledges were built for men of learning &amp; towardneſſe. Laſtly if we wil be truly thankful, we may not haue any liking of ſuch as are well ſchooled &amp; taught to flatter, which can ducke like Friers &amp; kiſſe the ground w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their knées which haue teares at commandement, which can counterfet &amp; liuely expreſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> countenance and ſpéech of others, &amp; can diſſemble verie cunningly. Theſe men are the worſt, &amp; the verieſt diſhclouts of all other, they are like to the Cameleon. Though they be born in England, they are but baſtard Engliſhmen, whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and whoſoeuer they be, they are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie of the loweſt place. But I haue ſpoken to muche of theſe graceleſſe fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes whom I ſhould not haue honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſo much as to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber them though to their diſcommendation. I doe fréely confeſſe that there is in our Vniuerſitie a goodly nomber of excellent wittes: if I ſhold not, I might by me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be iuſtly char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with &amp; conuinced of a lye, and by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God of vnthankfulnes. I do not enuie the good eſtate of the Vniuerſitie:
<pb facs="tcp:1086:16"/> thankes be to God for this worthie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and I doe humbly pray his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie that this happie harueſt may be more plentiful then euen now it is. And becauſe I haue gone thus farre in the mention of ſharpe wittes, I am verie earneſtly to intreate you which are ſet ouer the Colledges of our Vniuerſitie, that you will account of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which haue ſhewed ſingular proofe of learning, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and vertue in our Colledges &amp; V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſitie as of your deare brethren, and your owne bowels: and that you will make much of thoſe young men &amp; ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of lower place but yet of excellent hope. So ſhal our <hi>Colledges</hi> (as the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple trée of Perſia) budde, bloſſome, and beare fruite all times of the yeare, The Church of England ſhall be better fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed then it is, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorie of God more brightly ſhine amongſt vs. As for you (my welbeloued brethren) giue your ſelues wholy to learning and godlines, neither take it grieuouſly, if you be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten a time, when prefermentes are beſtowed. Liue in peace and the God of peace ſhall be with you. If ye put in practiſe theſe thinges whiche I haue in
<pb facs="tcp:1086:17"/> godly ſorte deliuered: whether wee be Maſters, fellowes or Schollers of Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, it will eaſily appeare, that wée haue rendred to God, <hi>The calues of our lippes,</hi> that is to ſay, that we haue very humbly both in worde and déede, giuen thankes to his Maieſtie. My meaning is to reſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next verſe vntill another time: here therfore I wil make an end. The eternal God and mercifull father giue vs grace, vnfaignedly to turne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, earneſtly to pray to his maieſty, &amp; to obtaine at his hands that we pray for, laſtly, for his infinite benefites to prayſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ceaſſing the infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God the Father, to whome with the Sonne, and the holie Ghoſte, be all prayſe, honour, and glorie for euer.</p>
               <closer>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</closer>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>2. Cor. 13.13.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>The grace of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, the loue of God, and the fellowſhip of the holie Ghoſte be with you all. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:1086:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
